<resource xmlns="http://da-ra.de/schema/kernel-4" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://www.da-ra.de/dara/schemadefinitions/dara.xsd">
	<!--
da|ra 4.0 Documentation for Study 'ALLBUS/GGSS 1988 (Allgemeine Bevölkerungsumfrage der 
Sozialwissenschaften/German General Social 
Survey 1988)
'
-->
	<!--
da|ra 4.0 Dokumentation für Studie 'Allgemeine Bevölkerungsumfrage der Sozialwissenschaften ALLBUS 1988
'
-->
	<resourceType>Dataset</resourceType>
	<resourceTypesFree>
		<resourceTypeFree>
			<language>de</language>
			<typeName>Numerisch</typeName>
		</resourceTypeFree>
		<resourceTypeFree>
			<language>en</language>
			<typeName>Numeric</typeName>
		</resourceTypeFree>
	</resourceTypesFree>
	<resourceIdentifier>
		<identifier>ZA1670</identifier>
		<currentVersion>1.0.0</currentVersion>
	</resourceIdentifier>
	<titles>
		<title>
			<language>de</language>
			<titleName>Allgemeine Bevölkerungsumfrage der Sozialwissenschaften ALLBUS 1988
</titleName>
		</title>
		<title>
			<language>en</language>
			<titleName>ALLBUS/GGSS 1988 (Allgemeine Bevölkerungsumfrage der 
Sozialwissenschaften/German General Social 
Survey 1988)
</titleName>
		</title>
	</titles>
	<creators>
		<creator>
			<institution>
				<institutionName>GESIS - Leibniz-Institut für Sozialwissenschaften</institutionName>
			</institution>
		</creator>
	</creators>
	<dataURLs>
		<dataURL>https://search.gesis.org/research_data/ZA1670?doi=10.4232/1.1670</dataURL>
	</dataURLs>
	<doiProposal>10.4232/1.1670</doiProposal>
	<publicationDate>
		<year>2002</year>
	</publicationDate>
	<availability>
		<availabilityType>Download</availabilityType>
		<availabilityFree>
			<language>de</language>
			<freetext>A - Daten und Dokumente sind für die akademische Forschung und Lehre freigegeben.</freetext>
		</availabilityFree>
		<availabilityFree>
			<language>en</language>
			<freetext>A - Data and documents are released for academic research and teaching.</freetext>
		</availabilityFree>
	</availability>
	<rights>
		<right>
			<language>de</language>
			<freetext>Alle im GESIS DBK veröffentlichten Metadaten sind frei verfügbar unter den Creative Commons CC0 1.0 Universal Public Domain Dedication. GESIS bittet jedoch darum, dass Sie alle Metadatenquellen anerkennen und sie nennen, etwa die Datengeber oder jeglichen Aggregator, inklusive GESIS selbst. Für weitere Informationen siehe https://dbk.gesis.org/dbksearch/guidelines.asp?db=d </freetext>
		</right>
		<right>
			<language>en</language>
			<freetext>All metadata from GESIS DBK are available free of restriction under the Creative Commons CC0 1.0 Universal Public Domain Dedication. However, GESIS requests that you actively acknowledge and give attribution to all metadata sources, such as the data providers and any data aggregators, including GESIS. For further information see https://dbk.gesis.org/dbksearch/guidelines.asp </freetext>
		</right>
	</rights>
	<resourceLanguage>deu</resourceLanguage>
	<alternativeIDs>
		<alternativeID>
			<identifier>ZA1670</identifier>
			<type>ZA-No.</type>
		</alternativeID>
		<alternativeID>
			<identifier>ALLBUS</identifier>
			<type>FDZ</type>
		</alternativeID>
	</alternativeIDs>
	<classifications>
		<classification>
			<classificationInternal>
				<classificationSchemaType>ZA</classificationSchemaType>
				<identifiers>
					<identifier>KAT50</identifier>
					<!-- Gesellschaft, Kultur -->
				</identifiers>
			</classificationInternal>
		</classification>
		<classification>
			<classificationExternal>
				<language>de</language>
				<classificationSchema>CESSDA Topic Classification</classificationSchema>
				<terms>
					<term>Migration</term>
					<term>Kulturelle und nationale Identität</term>
					<term>Spezifische Krankheiten, Störungen und Gesundheitsprobleme</term>
					<term>Politisches Verhalten und politische Einstellungen</term>
					<term>Regierung, politische Systeme, Parteien und Organisationen</term>
					<term>Familie und Ehe</term>
					<term>Geschlecht und Geschlechterrollen</term>
					<term>Umweltschutz und Naturschutz</term>
				</terms>
			</classificationExternal>
		</classification>
		<classification>
			<classificationExternal>
				<language>en</language>
				<classificationSchema>CESSDA Topic Classification</classificationSchema>
				<terms>
					<term>Migration</term>
					<term>Cultural and national identity</term>
					<term>Specific diseases, disorders and medical conditions</term>
					<term>Political behaviour and attitudes</term>
					<term>Government, political systems and organisations</term>
					<term>Family life and marriage</term>
					<term>Gender and gender roles</term>
					<term>Environment and conservation</term>
				</terms>
			</classificationExternal>
		</classification>
	</classifications>
	<descriptions>
		<description>
			<language>de</language>
			<freetext>Die Allgemeine Bevölkerungsumfrage der Sozialwissenschaften (ALLBUS) ist eine Trenderhebung, in der seit 1980 alle zwei Jahre eine Zufallsstichprobe der deutschen Bevölkerung befragt wird. Das primäre Ziel des Umfrageprogramms ist die Beobachtung von Einstellungen, Verhalten und sozialen Wandel in Deutschland. Jede ALLBUS-Querschnittserhebung besteht aus ein oder zwei Schwerpunktmodulen zu wechselnden Themen. Diese werden ergänzt durch weitere inhaltliche Fragen und ein Kernmodul mit detaillierten demografischen Informationen. Zudem werden Zusatzinformation zum Interview und den Interviewern bereitgestellt. Die Schwerpunktmodule folgen in der Regel einem 10-jährigen Replikationszyklus, viele Einzelindikatoren und Itembatterien werden aber auch in kürzeren Abständen repliziert. 
Seit Mitte der 1980er Jahre werden zusammen mit ALLBUS auch regelmäßig ein oder zwei Module des ISSP (International Social Survey Programme) erhoben.
Das Schwerpunktmodul des ALLBUS/GGSS 1988 behandelt das Thema „Politische Partizipation und Einstellungen zum politischen System“. Neben Fragen zu konventioneller und unkonventioneller politischer Partizipation, enthält das Modul Fragen zur politischen Sozialisation, politischem Wissen, politischer Unterstützung usw. Weitere Themen sind u.a. Einstellungen und Kontakte zu Gastarbeitern, die Wahrnehmung von Umweltbelastungen und Fragen zum Thema AIDS (HIV). Zusätzlich ist das ISSP Modul „Familie und sich ändernde Geschlechtsrollen“ enthalten. </freetext>
			<descriptionType>Abstract</descriptionType>
		</description>
		<description>
			<language>de</language>
			<freetext>1. Einstellungen zu Ehe, Familie und Partnerschaft: Familie alsGlücksvoraussetzung; Heirat bei dauernder Partnerschaft; Wichtigkeit derFamilie; Arbeitsteilung im Haushalt.
2. Einstellungen und Kontakte zu Gastarbeitern: Einstellungsskala;Kontakte zu Gastarbeitern in der Familie, am Arbeitsplatz, in derNachbarschaft oder im Freundeskreis.
3. Wahrnehmung von Umweltbelastungen: Einschätzung der allgemeinen wieauch der persönlichen Belastung durch Fluglärm, Bleigehalt im Benzin,Industrieabwässer, Industrieabgase, Kernkraftwerke, Verkehrslärm undAutoabgase.
4. Politische Partizipation: Häufigkeit ausgewählter politischerAktivitäten; eigene Teilnahme bzw. Beteiligungsbereitschaft anausgewählten Protestformen; präferierte Formen politischerPartizipation; eigene Wahlberechtigung und Teilnahme an den letztenLandtags- und Bundestagswahlen; Einschätzung der eigenen Kompetenz inpolitischen Fragen.
5. Einstellungen zum politischen System: Zufriedenheit mit dem Lebenin der Bundesrepublik; Gefühl politischer Wirksamkeit undRepräsentiertheit durch Politiker; Legitimität sozialer Ungleichheit;Einstellung zur Demokratie; Zufriedenheit mit der Demokratie und demFunktionieren des politischen System in der Bundesrepublik (politischeUnterstützung).
6. Nationalstolz: Stolz auf deutsche Einrichtungen und deutscheLeistungen.
7. Politische Einstellungen: Einstellung zu den sozialen Unterschiedenin der Bundesrepublik; politischesInteresse; Postmaterialismus (Wichtigkeit von Ruhe und Ordnung, vonBürgereinfluss, vonInflationsbekämpfung und von freier Meinungsäußerung); Selbsteinstufungauf einem Links-Rechts-Kontinuum;Einstellung zu Extremisten als Lehrer; Einstellung zur Todesstrafe fürTerroristen und Kindesmörder;Selbsteinschätzung der sozialen Schichtzugehörigkeit; Wahlverhalten beider letzten Bundestagswahl;Parteipräferenz der Eltern zur Jugendzeit des Befragten.
8. Fragen zum Thema AIDS (HIV): Kenntnis der Krankheit AIDS;wahrgenommene Berichte über AIDS in den Medien; Beurteilung des eigenenAnsteckungsrisikos bezüglich ausgewählter Kontaktformen; vermuteteEntwicklung der durch AIDS verursachten Todesfälle; Meinung zurWahrscheinlichkeit der Entwicklung eines Medikaments gegen AIDS;Einstellung zu staatlichen Aufklärungs- und Zwangsmaßnahmen; Einstellungzu höheren Krankenversicherungsbeiträgen für HIV-Infizierte; Einstellungzur Entlassung infizierter Arbeitnehmer und einem Einreiseverbot fürHIV-infizierte Ausländer; Einstellung zu einer zentralen Meldepflicht;Sorge vor einer eigenen HIV-Infektion sowie von Familienmitgliedern undFreunden; eigene Schutzmaßnahmen und Verhaltensänderungen; persönlicheBekanntschaft mit HIV-Infizierten.
9. ALLBUS-Demographie: Angaben zur befragten Person: Geschlecht;Geburtsmonat, Geburtsjahr, Alter; Geschwister; Wohnort (Bundesland,Regierungsbezirk, politische Gemeindegröße, Boustedt-Gemeindetyp);Konfession, Kirchgangshäufigkeit; Wahlabsicht (Sonntagsfrage);Schulbesuch, allgemeiner Schulabschluss, berufliche Ausbildung;Erwerbsstatus; Angaben zum gegenwärtigen Beruf, Branche, wöchentlicheArbeitsdauer; Zeitpunkt der Aufgabe hauptberuflicher Erwerbstätigkeit;Unterbrechung der Erwerbstätigkeit; Angaben zum ehemaligen Beruf; Dauervon Arbeitslosigkeit; Wunsch nach Arbeit; vorwiegender Lebensunterhalt,Befragteneinkommen; Alter beim Verlassen des Elternhauses;Familienstand; Ehebiographie.
Angaben zum gegenwärtigen Ehepartner:Alter; gegenwärtiger Schulbesuch, allgemeiner Schulabschluss, beruflicheAusbildung; Erwerbsstatus; wöchentliche Arbeitsdauer; Angaben zumgegenwärtigen Beruf; Zeitpunkt der Aufgabe hauptberuflicherErwerbstätigkeit.
Angaben zum ehemaligen Ehepartner: Alter; allgemeiner Schulabschluss,berufliche Ausbildung; Angaben zum Beruf.
Angaben zum nichtehelichen Lebenspartner: Dauer des Zusammenseins;Gemeinsamer Haushalt mit Lebenspartner; Aufgabenteilung im Haushalt;Geburtsmonat, Geburtsjahr, Alter; Schulbesuch, allgemeinerSchulabschluss, berufliche Ausbildung; Erwerbsstatus, Angaben zumgegenwärtigen bzw. zum ehemaligen Beruf, wöchentliche Arbeitsdauer.
Angaben zu den Eltern des Befragten: Allgemeiner Schulabschluss undberufliche Ausbildung von Mutter und Vater; Angaben zum Beruf desVaters; leben Eltern noch.
Haushaltsbeschreibung: Haushaltsgröße, Anzahl von über 17-jährigenHaushaltspersonen (reduzierte Haushaltsgröße); Kinder;Haushaltseinkommen; Wohnungstyp; Telefonanschluß.
Angaben zu den einzelnen Haushaltspersonen (Haushaltsliste):Verwandtschaft der Haushaltspersonen zum Befragten; Geschlecht derPersonen; ihr Geburtsmonat, Geburtsjahr, Alter; Familienstand.
Angaben zum Alter von Kindern außerhalb des Haushalts; Geburts- undTodesjahr verstorbener Kinder.
Gegenwärtige Mitgliedschaften des Befragten (DeutscherGewerkschaftsbund (DGB), Deutsche Angestelltengewerkschaft (DAG),Christlicher Gewerkschaftsbund (CGB), Union Leitender Angestellter(ULA), Deutscher Beamtenbund (DBB), Bauernverband, Gewerbeverband,Bundesverband der Deutschen Industrie (BDI), Berufsverband der freienBerufe, sonstiger Berufsverband; Gesangverein, Sportverein, Hobby-Vereinigung, Heimat- oder Bürgerverein, sonstige gesellige Vereinigung,Vertriebenen- oder Flüchtlingsverband, Wohlfahrtsverband, kirchlicheroder religiöser Verein, Jugend- oder Studentenorganisation, politischePartei, Bürgerinitiative, andere Vereine oder Verbände).
10. Daten zum Interview (Paradaten): Anwesenheit Dritter beim Interview; EingriffeDritter in das Interview; Kooperationsbereitschaft und Zuverlässigkeitder Angaben des Befragten; Interviewdauer; Interviewdatum;Interviewergeschlecht; Intervieweralter.
11. Familie und sich ändernde Geschlechtsrollen I (ISSP): Einstellungzur Berufstätigkeit von Frauen; Wichtigkeit einer eigenenBerufstätigkeit; präferierter Umfang der Berufstätigkeit von Frauenwährend verschiedener Phasen der Kindererziehung; präferierteBetreuungsmaßnahmen für Kleinkinder bei berufstätigen Eltern;Einstellung zu Partnerschaft, Ehe und Heirat; Einstellung zu alleinerziehenden Vätern und Müttern; Einstellung zu einem Recht auf Heiratfür homosexuelle Paare; ideale Kinderzahl und Beurteilung ausgewählterFamiliengrößen; Einstellung zu Kindern; Meinung über dasScheidungsrecht; Präferenz für Scheidung oder Zusammenbleiben in einergestörten Ehe; Berufstätigkeit der Mutter während der Kindheit desBefragten; eigene Scheidungen.
Verheiratete wurden zusätzlich gefragt: Frühere Scheidung des jetzigenEhepartners; Zusammenleben mit Partner vor der Heirat und Beginn desZusammenlebens; Umfang der Berufstätigkeit während verschiedener Phasender Kindererziehung.
12. Ergänzungen und abgeleitete Variablen: Berufsvercodung gemäß ISCO (InternationalStandard Classification of Occupations) 1968; Berufsprestige (nachTreiman); Magnitudeprestige (nach Wegener); Transformationsgewicht.</freetext>
			<descriptionType>TableOfContents</descriptionType>
		</description>
		<description>
			<language>en</language>
			<freetext>ALLBUS (GGSS - the German General Social Survey) is a biennial trend survey based on random samples of the German population. Established in 1980, its mission is to monitor attitudes, behavior, and social change in Germany. Each ALLBUS cross-sectional survey consists of one or two main question modules covering changing topics, a range of supplementary questions and a core module providing detailed demographic information. Additionally, data on the interview and the interviewers are provided as well. Key topics generally follow a 10-year replication cycle, many individual indicators and item batteries are replicated at shorter intervals.
Since the mid-1980ies ALLBUS also regularly hosts one or two modules of the ISSP (International Social Survey Programme).
The main topic of ALLBUS/GGSS 1988 is “Political Participation and Attitudes toward the Political System,” with questions on political participation (both conventional and unconventional), political socialization and competence, political support, etc. Other topics include attitudes towards and contacts with foreign guest-workers, perceptions of environmental pollution, and questions about AIDS (HIV). Additionally included is the ISSP module "Family and Changing Gender Roles." </freetext>
			<descriptionType>Abstract</descriptionType>
		</description>
		<description>
			<language>en</language>
			<freetext>1.) Attitudes towards marriage, family, and partnership:family as a prerequisite for happiness; marriage in case of steadypartnership; importance of the family; arrangement of duties in thehousehold.
2.) Attitudes towards and contacts with foreign guest-workers(Gastarbeiter): scale of attitudes towards foreigners; contacts with guest-workers withinthe family, at work, in the neighborhood, or among friends.
3.) Perception of environmental pollution: estimation of personal andoverall hazard through lead content of petrol, industrial sewage,industrial fumes, nuclear power plants, traffic noise, and exhaustfumes.
4.) Political participation: frequency of various politicalactivities; personal participation or willingness to participate inselected forms of protest; preferred form of political participation;respondent´s eligibility to vote and participation in general federalelections or state elections (Landtagswahl); self-assessment ofpolitical competence.
5.) Attitudes towards the political system: satisfaction with life inthe Federal Republic; feeling of political effectiveness andrepresentation by politicians; legitimacy of social inequality; variousattitudes towards democracy; satisfaction with democracy and opinion onthe performance of the German political system (political support).
6.) National pride: pride in German institutions and achievements.
7.) Political attitudes: attitude towards social differences in the Federal Republic; political interest; postmaterialism (importance of law and order, fighting rising prices, free expression of opinions, andinfluence on governmental decisions); self-placement on a left-rightcontinuum; attitude towards extremists as teachers; attitude towardsthe death penalty for terrorists and murderers of children;self-assessment of social class; recall of past vote; party preferenceof parents during youth of respondent.
8.) Questions on AIDS (HIV): knowledge about the disease AIDS;perceived reports on AIDS in the media; assessment of personal risk ofinfection regarding selected forms of contact; expected development ofcases of death caused by AIDS; opinion on the probability of developingmedication against AIDS; attitude towards governmental information andrepressive measures; attitude towards higher health insurance fees forthose infected with AIDS; attitude towards firing infected employeesand towards entry refusal for foreigners infected with AIDS; attitudetowards a central registration requirement; concern about personal AIDSinfection and infection of family members and friends; personalprotective measures and behavioral changes; acquaintance withAIDS-infected people.
9.) ALLBUS-Demography: Details about the respondent: gender; month andyear of birth, age; place of residence (federal state, administrativeregion, size of municipality, Boustedt-type of municipality); religiousdenomination, frequency of church attendance; voting intention(Sonntagsfrage); currently at school or university, general education,vocational training; employment status; details about currentoccupation, industrial sector, working hours per week; date oftermination of full- or part-time employment; gaps in occupationalbiography; details about former occupation; length of unemployment;desire for employment; principal source of livelihood; respondent´sincome; age when leaving parental home; marital status; maritalbiography.
Details about respondent´s current spouse: age; currently at school oruniversity, general education, vocational training; employment status;employment status; working hours per week; details about currentoccupation; date of termination of full- or part-time employment.
Details about respondent´s former spouse: age; general education,vocational training; details about current occupation.
Details about respondent´s steady extra-marital partner: length ofrelationship; common household; distribution of household chores; monthand year of birth, age; currently at school or university, generaleducation, vocational training; employment status; details aboutcurrent and former occupation respectively; working hours per week.
Details about respondent´s parents: general education and vocationaltraining of father and mother; father´s occupation; parents stillalive. Composition of household: size of household; number of personsolder than 17 in household (reduced size of household); children;household income; type of dwelling; telephone.
Details about household members: relation to respondent; gender; monthand year of birth, age; marital status.
Respondent´s current memberships (Deutscher Gewerkschaftsbund (DGB,blue-collar union), Deutsche Angestelltengewerkschaft (DAG,white-collar union), Christlicher Gewerkschaftsbund (CGB, Christianunion), Union Leitender Angestellter (ULA, association of managers),Deutscher Beamtenbund (DBB, public service union), farmer´sassociation, trade association, Bundesverband der Deutschen Industrie(BDI), association of German industry), association of a liberalprofession, other occupational association; choral society, sportsclub, leisure activity club, local history or community club, othersocial association, association of German expellees or refugees,charitable association, religious/church organization, youth or studentorganization, political party, citizens´ action group, other club orassociation).
10.) Data on the interview (paradata): presence of other people during theinterview; intervention of other people in the course of the interview;willingness of respondent to cooperate; evaluation of respondent´sreliability; length of interview; date of interview; gender ofinterviewer; age of interviewer.
11.) Family and changing gender roles I (ISSP): attitude towardsemployment of women; the importance of personal employment; preferredextent of employment of women during different stages of child raising;preferred type of child care for working couples; attitude towardspartnership, marriage and wedding; attitude towards single fathers ormothers; attitude towards a right for homosexual couples to getmarried; ideal number of children and opinion on various family sizes;attitude towards children; opinion on divorce law; preference fordivorce or for continuation of a disturbed marriage; employment ofmother during childhood of respondent; personal divorces.
Married respondents were also asked about: previous divorce of presentspouse; pre-marital cohabitation with partner and beginning ofcohabitation; extent of employment during different phases of childraising.
12.) Added value: International Standard Classification ofOccupations (ISCO 1968); occupational prestige (according to Treiman);magnitude prestige (according to Wegener); weights. </freetext>
			<descriptionType>TableOfContents</descriptionType>
		</description>
	</descriptions>
	<geographicCoverages>
		<geographicCoverage>
			<geographicCoverageControlled>DE</geographicCoverageControlled>
			<geographicCoveragesFree>
				<geographicCoverageFree>
					<language>en</language>
					<freetext>FRG incl. West Berlin</freetext>
				</geographicCoverageFree>
				<geographicCoverageFree>
					<language>de</language>
					<freetext>BRD einschl. West-Berlin
	
</freetext>
				</geographicCoverageFree>
			</geographicCoveragesFree>
		</geographicCoverage>
	</geographicCoverages>
	<universes>
		<universe>
			<language>de</language>
			<sampled>In Privathaushalten lebende deutsche Staatsangehörige ab 18 Jahren</sampled>
		</universe>
		<universe>
			<language>en</language>
			<sampled>Private households addressing all individuals with German citizenship
who were at least 18 years of age by the day of the interview.</sampled>
		</universe>
	</universes>
	<samplings>
		<sampling>
			<language>de</language>
			<method>Wahrscheinlichkeitsauswahl: Mehrstufige Zufallsauswahl; Auswahlverfahren Kommentar: Haushaltsstichprobe: Mehrstufig geschichtete Zufallsauswahl
(ADM-Mastersample) </method>
		</sampling>
		<sampling>
			<language>en</language>
			<method>Probability: Multistage; Sampling Procedure Comment: Household Sample: Multi-stage random sample (ADM-Mastersample) </method>
		</sampling>
	</samplings>
	<temporalCoverages>
		<temporalCoverage>
			<temporalCoverageFormal>
				<startDate>
					<monthyear>1988-04</monthyear>
				</startDate>
				<endDate>
					<monthyear>1988-07</monthyear>
				</endDate>
			</temporalCoverageFormal>
		</temporalCoverage>
	</temporalCoverages>
	<timeDimensions>
		<timeDimension>
			<timeDimensionType>CrossSection</timeDimensionType>
		</timeDimension>
	</timeDimensions>
	<contributors>
		<contributor>
			<person>
				<firstName>Karl U.</firstName>
				<middleName/>
				<lastName>Mayer</lastName>
				<contributorType>Researcher</contributorType>
				<affiliation>
					<affiliationName>Max-Planck-Institut für Bildungsforschung, Berlin</affiliationName>
				</affiliation>
			</person>
		</contributor>
		<contributor>
			<person>
				<firstName>Walter</firstName>
				<middleName/>
				<lastName>Müller</lastName>
				<contributorType>Researcher</contributorType>
				<affiliation>
					<affiliationName>Universität Mannheim</affiliationName>
				</affiliation>
			</person>
		</contributor>
		<contributor>
			<person>
				<firstName>Franz U.</firstName>
				<middleName/>
				<lastName>Pappi</lastName>
				<contributorType>Researcher</contributorType>
				<affiliation>
					<affiliationName>Universität Kiel</affiliationName>
				</affiliation>
			</person>
		</contributor>
		<contributor>
			<person>
				<firstName>Erwin K.</firstName>
				<middleName/>
				<lastName>Scheuch</lastName>
				<contributorType>Researcher</contributorType>
				<affiliation>
					<affiliationName>Universität Köln</affiliationName>
				</affiliation>
			</person>
		</contributor>
		<contributor>
			<person>
				<firstName>Rolf</firstName>
				<middleName/>
				<lastName>Ziegler</lastName>
				<contributorType>Researcher</contributorType>
				<affiliation>
					<affiliationName>Universität München
</affiliationName>
				</affiliation>
			</person>
		</contributor>
		<contributor>
			<institution>
				<institutionName>GFM-GETAS, Hamburg
</institutionName>
				<contributorType>DataCollector</contributorType>
			</institution>
		</contributor>
	</contributors>
	<collectionModes>
		<collectionMode><collectionModeType>Interview.FaceToFace.PAPI</collectionModeType></collectionMode>
		<collectionMode><collectionModeType>SelfAdministeredQuestionnaire.Paper</collectionModeType></collectionMode>
		<collectionMode>
			<collectionModesFree>
				<collectionModeFree>
					<language>de</language>
					<freetext>Mündliche Befragung mit standardisiertem Fragebogen und schriftliche
Zusatzbefragung (drop off) im Rahmen des ISSP
</freetext>
				</collectionModeFree>
				<collectionModeFree>
					<language>en</language>
					<freetext>Personal interview with standardized questionnaire (PAPI - Paper and
Pencil Interviewing), additional self-completion questionnaire (drop
off) for ISSP </freetext>
				</collectionModeFree>
			</collectionModesFree>
		</collectionMode>
	</collectionModes>
	<dataSets>
		<dataSet>
			<unitType>Individual</unitType>
			<numberUnits>3052</numberUnits>
			<numberVariables>603</numberVariables>
		</dataSet>
	</dataSets>
	<notes>
		<note>
			<language>de</language>
			<text>Es wurde ein Fragebogen mit Split verwendet. Bei den Fragen zur
politischen Partizipation wurde aus
methodischen Überlegungen die Reihenfolge der Fragen variiert.
Eine in der Demographie vereinfachte Version des Datensatzes ist als
ALLBUScompact 1988 (ZA-Studien-Nr. 3712) zusätzlich vorhanden.
</text>
		</note>
		<note>
			<language>en</language>
			<text>A ´split questionnaire´ was used for questions on political
participation. The sequence of the questionnaire was varied due to
methodological considerations. A second version of this data set with a
shortened demography module is available as ALLBUScompact 1988 (ZA No.
3712). </text>
		</note>
	</notes>
	<publications>
		<publication>
			<unstructuredPublication>
				<freetext>Braun, Michael; Mohler, Peter Ph.: 
Die Allgemeine Bevölkerungsumfrage der Sozialwissenschaften (ALLBUS). Rückblick und Ausblick in die neunziger Jahre. 
In: ZUMA-Nachrichten 29, 1991, S. 7-28. 
</freetext>
			</unstructuredPublication>
		</publication>
		<publication>
			<unstructuredPublication>
				<freetext>Terwey, Michael: 
ALLBUS: Das Programm und Erweiterungen des bestehenden Angebots. 
In: ZA-Information 42, 1998, S. 33-43. 
</freetext>
			</unstructuredPublication>
		</publication>
		<publication>
			<unstructuredPublication>
				<freetext>Terwey, Michael: 
ALLBUS: A German General Social Survey. 
Schmollers Jahrbuch 120, 2000, S. 151-158. 
</freetext>
			</unstructuredPublication>
		</publication>
		<publication>
			<unstructuredPublication>
				<freetext>Terwey, Michael: 
Zum aktuellen Wandel im Zugriff auf ALLBUS-Materialien und zur ALLBUS-Nutzung in Publikationen. 
In: ZA-Information 53, 2003, S. 195-202. 
</freetext>
			</unstructuredPublication>
		</publication>
		<publication>
			<unstructuredPublication>
				<freetext>Veröffentlichungsreihe "Blickpunkt Gesellschaft": 
Müller, Walter; Mohler, Peter Ph.; Erbslöh, Barbara; Wasmer, Martina (Hrsg.): 
Blickpunkt Gesellschaft: Einstellungen und Verhalten der Bundesbürger. 
Opladen: Westdeutscher Verlag 1990. 
</freetext>
			</unstructuredPublication>
		</publication>
		<publication>
			<unstructuredPublication>
				<freetext>Mohler, Peter Ph.; Bandilla, Wolfgang (Hrsg.): 
Blickpunkt Gesellschaft: 2. Einstellungen und Verhalten der Bundesbürger in Ost und West. 
Opladen: Westdeutscher Verlag 1992. 
</freetext>
			</unstructuredPublication>
		</publication>
		<publication>
			<unstructuredPublication>
				<freetext>Braun, Michael; Mohler, Peter Ph. (Hrsg.): 
Blickpunkt Gesellschaft: 3. Einstellungen und Verhalten der Bundesbürger. 
Opladen: Westdeutscher Verlag 1994. 
</freetext>
			</unstructuredPublication>
		</publication>
		<publication>
			<unstructuredPublication>
				<freetext>Braun, Michael; Mohler, Peter Ph. (Hrsg.): 
Blickpunkt Gesellschaft: 4. Soziale Ungleichheit in Deutschland. 
Opladen: Westdeutscher Verlag 1998. 
</freetext>
			</unstructuredPublication>
		</publication>
		<publication>
			<unstructuredPublication>
				<freetext>Alba, Richard; Schmidt, Peter; Wasmer, Martina (Hrsg.): 
Blickpunkt Gesellschaft: 5. Deutsche und Ausländer: Freunde, Fremde oder Feinde? 
Wiesbaden: Westdeutscher Verlag 2000. 
</freetext>
			</unstructuredPublication>
		</publication>
		<publication>
			<unstructuredPublication>
				<freetext>Koch, Achim; Wasmer, Martina; Schmidt, Peter (Hrsg.): 
Blickpunkt Gesellschaft: 6. Politische Partizipation in der Bundesrepublik Deutschland. Empirische Befunde und theoretische Erklärungen. 
Opladen: Leske + Budrich 2001. 
</freetext>
			</unstructuredPublication>
		</publication>
		<publication>
			<unstructuredPublication>
				<freetext>Alba, Richard; Schmidt, Peter; Wasmer, Martina (Hrsg.): 
Germans or Foreigners? Attitudes Towards Ethnic Minorities in Post-Reunification Germany. 
New York und Houndmills: Palgrave Macmillan 2003.</freetext>
			</unstructuredPublication>
		</publication></publications>
</resource>
