<resource xmlns="http://da-ra.de/schema/kernel-4" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://www.da-ra.de/dara/schemadefinitions/dara.xsd">
	<!--
da|ra 4.0 Documentation for Study 'German Emigration and Remigration Panel Study (GERPS) 2019'
-->
	<!--
da|ra 4.0 Dokumentation für Studie 'German Emigration and Remigration Panel Study (GERPS) 2019'
-->
	<resourceType>Dataset</resourceType>
	<resourceTypesFree>
		<resourceTypeFree>
			<language>de</language>
			<typeName>Numerisch</typeName>
		</resourceTypeFree>
		<resourceTypeFree>
			<language>en</language>
			<typeName>Numeric</typeName>
		</resourceTypeFree>
	</resourceTypesFree>
	<resourceIdentifier>
		<identifier>ZA7584</identifier>
		<currentVersion>1.0.1</currentVersion>
	</resourceIdentifier>
	<titles>
		<title>
			<language>de</language>
			<titleName>German Emigration and Remigration Panel Study (GERPS) 2019</titleName>
		</title>
		<title>
			<language>en</language>
			<titleName>German Emigration and Remigration Panel Study (GERPS) 2019</titleName>
		</title>
	</titles>
	<creators>
		<creator>
			<person>
				<firstName>Marcel</firstName>
				<middleName/>
				<lastName>Erlinghagen</lastName>
				<affiliation>
					<affiliationName>University of Duisburg-Essen</affiliationName>
				</affiliation>
			</person>
		</creator>
		<creator>
			<person>
				<firstName>Norbert</firstName>
				<middleName/>
				<lastName>Schneider</lastName>
				<affiliation>
					<affiliationName>Federal Institute of Population Research (BiB), Wiesbaden</affiliationName>
				</affiliation>
			</person>
		</creator>
	</creators>
	<dataURLs>
		<dataURL>https://search.gesis.org/research_data/ZA7584?doi=10.4232/1.13943</dataURL>
	</dataURLs>
	<doiProposal>10.4232/1.13943</doiProposal>
	<publicationDate>
		<date>2022-06-30</date>
	</publicationDate>
	<publicationPlace>Cologne, Germany</publicationPlace>
	<publisher>
		<institution>
			<institutionName>GESIS</institutionName>
		</institution>
	</publisher>
	<availability>
		<availabilityType>Download</availabilityType>
		<availabilityFree>
			<language>de</language>
			<freetext>A - Daten und Dokumente sind für die akademische Forschung und Lehre freigegeben.</freetext>
		</availabilityFree>
		<availabilityFree>
			<language>en</language>
			<freetext>A - Data and documents are released for academic research and teaching.</freetext>
		</availabilityFree>
	</availability>
	<rights>
		<right>
			<language>de</language>
			<freetext>Alle im GESIS DBK veröffentlichten Metadaten sind frei verfügbar unter den Creative Commons CC0 1.0 Universal Public Domain Dedication. GESIS bittet jedoch darum, dass Sie alle Metadatenquellen anerkennen und sie nennen, etwa die Datengeber oder jeglichen Aggregator, inklusive GESIS selbst. Für weitere Informationen siehe https://dbk.gesis.org/dbksearch/guidelines.asp?db=d </freetext>
		</right>
		<right>
			<language>en</language>
			<freetext>All metadata from GESIS DBK are available free of restriction under the Creative Commons CC0 1.0 Universal Public Domain Dedication. However, GESIS requests that you actively acknowledge and give attribution to all metadata sources, such as the data providers and any data aggregators, including GESIS. For further information see https://dbk.gesis.org/dbksearch/guidelines.asp </freetext>
		</right>
	</rights>
	<resourceLanguage>deu</resourceLanguage>
	<alternativeIDs>
		<alternativeID>
			<identifier>ZA7584</identifier>
			<type>ZA-No.</type>
		</alternativeID>
	</alternativeIDs>
	<classifications>
		<classification>
			<classificationInternal>
				<classificationSchemaType>ZA</classificationSchemaType>
				<identifiers>
					<identifier>KAT38</identifier>
					<!-- Beruf -->
					<identifier>KAT39</identifier>
					<!-- Einkommen -->
					<identifier>KAT50</identifier>
					<!-- Gesellschaft, Kultur -->
					<identifier>KAT51</identifier>
					<!-- Gemeinde, Wohnumwelt -->
					<identifier>KAT53</identifier>
					<!-- Familie -->
					<identifier>KAT55</identifier>
					<!-- Erziehung, Schulwesen -->
					<identifier>KAT54</identifier>
					<!-- Person, Persönlichkeit, Rolle -->
				</identifiers>
			</classificationInternal>
		</classification>
		<classification>
			<classificationExternal>
				<language>de</language>
				<classificationSchema>CESSDA Topic Classification</classificationSchema>
				<terms>
					<term>Migration</term>
					<term>Beschäftigung und Erwerbstätigkeit</term>
					<term>Beschäftigungspolitik</term>
					<term>Ruhestand</term>
					<term>Arbeitslosigkeit</term>
					<term>Arbeitsbedingungen</term>
					<term>Soziale und berufliche Mobilität</term>
					<term>Soziale Lage und soziale Indikatoren</term>
					<term>PSYCHOLOGIE</term>
				</terms>
			</classificationExternal>
		</classification>
		<classification>
			<classificationExternal>
				<language>en</language>
				<classificationSchema>CESSDA Topic Classification</classificationSchema>
				<terms>
					<term>Migration</term>
					<term>Employment</term>
					<term>Labour and employment policy</term>
					<term>Retirement</term>
					<term>Unemployment</term>
					<term>Working conditions</term>
					<term>Social and occupational mobility</term>
					<term>Social conditions and indicators</term>
					<term>PSYCHOLOGY</term>
				</terms>
			</classificationExternal>
		</classification>
	</classifications>
	<descriptions>
		<description>
			<language>de</language>
			<freetext>Zielsetzung:Die German Emigration and Remigration Panel Study (GERPS) ist die Datenbasis, die im Rahmen des von der Deutschen Forschungsgemeinschaft (DFG) geförderten Projekts ´Individuelle Konsequenzen internationaler Migration im Lebensverlauf´ (Projektnummer 345626236) entwickelt wurde. GERPS verfolgt einen herkunftsbasierten Stichprobenansatz, der es erlaubt, individuelle Konsequenzen internationaler Migrationen aus einer Lebensverlaufsperspektive zu untersuchen. Neben dem Migrationsprozess und den soziodemographischen Merkmalen internationaler Migranten ist es das Ziel von GERPS, Längsschnittdaten über die vier folgenden Lebensbereiche zu erheben: Beschäftigung und Einkommen, Familie und Partnerschaft, Gesundheit und Wohlbefinden sowie soziale Netzwerke und Partizipation.
Methode:Das Studiendesign von GERPS nutzt Informationen aus deutschen Melderegistern für eine mehrstufig, geschichtete Wahrscheinlichkeitsstichprobe von Auswanderern und Rückwanderern mit deutscher Staatsangehörigkeit im Alter zwischen 20 und 70 Jahren mit einer dokumentierten internationalen Migration zwischen Juli 2017 und Juni 2018. GERPS umfasst derzeit vier Wellen, die einen Zeitraum von 24 Monaten abdecken. Die erste Welle startete im November 2018 und endete im Februar 2019. Die zweite Welle begann im Mai 2019, sechs Monate nach dem Beginn von Welle 1. Die dritte Welle startete im November 2019 und endete im Januar 2020, sechs Monate nach Beginn von Welle 2. Die vierte Welle ist für November 2020 geplant. Welle 1 umfasst Informationen über 4.545 Auswanderer und 6.465 Rückwanderer.
Analytisches Potenzial &amp; Fragebogen:Das Forschungsdesign ergänzt die traditionellen Befragungen von Zuwanderern in den wichtigsten Zielländern, indem es Auswanderer und Rückwanderer aus der Perspektive des Herkunftslandes befragt. Der herkunftsbezogene Stichprobenansatz hat drei wesentliche Vorteile im Vergleich zu traditionellen Ansätzen, bei denen die Stichproben aus Einwanderern in deren Zielländern gezogen werden: Erstens ermöglicht er vergleichende Studien von Auswanderern in verschiedenen Zielländern und von Rückkehrern aus verschiedenen Zielländern. Zweitens ermöglicht das Forschungsdesign, da GERPS als SOEP-nahe Studie konzipiert ist, Vergleiche der international mobilen Bevölkerung mit im Herkunftsland verbliebenen Nicht-Migranten durch Rückgriff auf das Sozioökonomische Panel (SOEP). Drittens erlaubt das Forschungsdesign vergleichende Studien über Auswanderer und Rückwanderer und bietet damit die Möglichkeit, die Folgen internationaler Migration aus mindestens zwei Perspektiven zu analysieren - kurz nach der Auswanderung und kurz nach der Rückkehr.Jede Welle von GERPS umfasst Fragen zur aktuellen Lebenssituation der deutschen Migranten in den verschiedenen Lebensbereichen, so dass Forschende mit jeder weiteren Welle schrittweise ein umfassendes Verständnis über die Lebensverläufe der Befragten gewinnen können. Zusätzlich hat jede Welle ihren eigenen Schwerpunkt: Die erste Welle erfasst Migrationsmotive und die Situation kurz vor der Migration. Dies ermöglicht die Realisierung eines hypothetischen fünften retrospektiven Messzeitpunkts, welcher es Forschenden erlaubt, Ursachen und Folgen der internationalen Migration von Anfang an zu untersuchen. Die zweite Welle fokussiert auf das Einkommen, die Arbeitsmarktintegration und die soziale Herkunft. Die dritte Welle erfasst insbesondere soziale und familiäre Beziehungen. Die vierte Welle wird durch ein offenes Modul ergänzt werden.
Die vorliegende Studie umfasst die Daten der zweiten Welle.</freetext>
			<descriptionType>Abstract</descriptionType>
		</description>
		<description>
			<language>de</language>
			<freetext>1. Screening-Modul zur Erfassung von Umzügen seit Welle 1: Umzug seit der letzten Befragung; Umzug innerhalb der Stadt/Gemeinde, in eine andere Stadt/Gemeinde, (zurück) nach Deutschland, (zurück) in das vorherige Land oder in ein anderes Land; Zeitpunkt des Umzugs; Entfernung der neuen Wohnung vom alten Wohnort (offen, Entfernungskategorie); Umzugsgründe (z.B. eigene berufliche Gründe bzw. berufliche Gründe des Partners, familiäre Gründe, finanzielle Gründe, etc.); Leichtigkeit des Zurechtfindens nach dem Umzug; Erfahrungen  mit Benachteiligung und Bevorzugung im Aufenthaltsland aufgrund der Herkunft.
2. Aktuelle Lebens- und Wohnsituation: Familienstand, Partnerschaft und Art des Haushalts: Haushaltsgröße; Haushaltszusammensetzung gleichgeblieben, verändert bzw. Befragter hat den vorherigen Haushalt verlassen; Haushaltsgröße zum Zeitpunkt der letzten Befragung; Aktualisierung der Angaben zur Haushaltszusammensetzung; Veränderung der Haushaltszusammensetzung (Person hinzugekommen, Person hat den Haushalt verlassen); Anzahl Personen im neuen Haushalt insgesamt (Haushaltsgröße) falls Befragter den vorherigen Haushalt verlassen hat; feste Partnerschaft; Umzug nach Deutschland und neue Wohnumgebung; Zeitpunkt des Umzugs nach Deutschland; Gründe und Motive für den Umzug (zurück) nach Deutschland; Auslandsaufenthalt nur für eine begrenzte Zeit geplant; Leichtigkeit des Zurechtfindens nach dem Umzug; treibende Kraft für die Umzugsentscheidung innerhalb der Partnerschaft; Umzug des Partners nach Deutschland  vor/ nach dem Befragten oder gleichzeitig bzw. lebte bereits in Deutschland; Zeitpunkt des Umzugs in das derzeitige Aufenthaltsland (Land W2); Kontakt zu Personen im Land vor dem Auslandsaufenthalt (enge Verwandte, weitere Verwandte, Arbeitskollegen bzw. sonstige Freunde und Bekannte); Gründe und Motive für den Umzug ins Ausland; Leichtigkeit des Zurechtfindens nach dem Umzug; derselbe Partner zum Zeitpunkt des Umzugs ins Ausland (Land W2); treibende Kraft für die Umzugsentscheidung innerhalb der Partnerschaft; Umzug des Partners in das Aufenthaltsland vor/ nach dem Befragten oder gleichzeitig bzw. lebte bereits dort; Lebenssituation drei Monate vor der letzten Emigration: Zeitpunkt des Umzugs ins Ausland (Monat und Jahr); vor dem Umzug ins Ausland in Deutschland gelebt; Haupttätigkeit vor dem Wegzug aus Deutschland.
3. Kontakte zu Freunden und Verwandten: Verbindung zu Deutschland und geplante Umzüge: seit dem Wegzug nicht mehr in Deutschland; Anzahl der Tage in Deutschland; ernsthafte Umzugsgedanken in ein anderes Land; Gründe für die Umzugsabsicht; geplante Dauer des Auslandsaufenthaltes (Land W2/ Deutschland) (höchstens noch ein Jahr, noch einige Jahre, für immer); geplante Dauer des Auslandsaufenthalts in Jahren; Kontakte mit Freuden und Verwandten: Anzahl enger Freunde/ Freundinnen; Anzahl enger Freunde in Deutschland, im aktuellen/ vorherigen Aufenthaltsland bzw. in einem anderen Land;  Kontaktintensität zu verschiedenen Gruppen in Deutschland (Ehepartner/ Partner, Eltern, Schwiegereltern, Geschwister, Enkel, Großeltern, andere Verwandte, enge Freunde). 
4. Erwerbsbiografie (Fokusmodul Welle 2):
Veränderung des Erwerbsstatus seit Ankunft: Gründe, warum die selbständige Tätigkeit aufgegeben wurde; Anzahl vorheriger Arbeitgeber; Beginn der Tätigkeit für den derzeitigen Arbeitgeber (Monat und Jahr); Beginn und Ende der Tätigkeit beim ersten Arbeitgeber (Monat und Jahr);; Beginn der Tätigkeit beim aktuellen Arbeitgeber (Monat und Jahr); derzeit nicht Erwerbstätige: frühere Erwerbstätigkeit;  Anzahl früherer Arbeitgeber bzw. frühere Selbständigkeit; Beginn und Ende der Tätigkeit für den ersten/ letzten Arbeitgeber (Monat und Jahr); vorherige Stellenzusage vor dem Umzug; Informationsquelle für diese Stelle; Art und Weise der Beendigung der früheren beruflichen Tätigkeit; zum Zeitpunkt des Ausscheidens bereits eine neue Stelle in Aussicht; Informationsquelle für diese neue Stelle; Art und Weise der Beendigung dieser früheren beruflichen Tätigkeit. 
Derzeitige Erwerbssituation: Branchenzugehörigkeit des derzeitigen Betriebs bzw. zum Zeitpunkt der letzten Befragung; Veränderung bezüglich des Arbeitgebers durch den Umzug in das Aufenthaltsland; Entsendung durch den Arbeitgeber; aktuelle Tätigkeit entspricht dem erlernten Beruf; für die Tätigkeit erforderliche Ausbildung;  amtliche Zulassung oder Erlaubnis zur Ausübung der beruflichen Tätigkeit in dem derzeitigen Aufenthaltsland (Land W2); Ausübung der Tätigkeit auch ohne amtliche Zulassung oder Erlaubnis möglich; befristetes Arbeitsverhältnis; Vorgesetztenfunktion; Anzahl Personen, für die Weisungsbefugnis besteht; Anzahl Beschäftigte des Gesamtunternehmens; Arbeitsstätte im Aufenthaltsland/ Deutschland; Arbeitsstätte in einem anderen Land; Betriebsbindung (persönliche Bedeutung, Zugehörigkeitsgefühl, Teil der Familie im Betrieb); Häufigkeit erhaltener Hilfe von Kollegen; Häufigkeit von Hilfsangeboten an Kollegen; Häufigkeit von ungerechter Kritik, Schikane oder Bloßstellung durch Kollegen und Vorgesetzte; Einschätzung der Chancen auf dem Arbeitsmarkt.
Selbständige und Freiberufler: Branchenzugehörigkeit des derzeitigen Betriebs bzw. zum Zeitpunkt der letzten Befragung; Anzahl der Mitarbeiter; Arbeitsstätte im Aufenthaltsland/ Deutschland; Arbeitsstätte in einem anderen Land; Wochenarbeitszeit; durchschnittlicher monatlicher Reingewinn (kategorisiert); aktuelle Tätigkeit entspricht dem erlernten Beruf; für die Tätigkeit erforderliche Ausbildung; amtliche Zulassung oder Erlaubnis zur Ausübung der beruflichen Tätigkeit in dem derzeitigen Aufenthaltsland (Land W2); Ausübung der Tätigkeit auch ohne amtliche Zulassung oder Erlaubnis möglich; Einschätzung der Chancen auf dem Arbeitsmarkt.
Nicht-Erwerbstätige: berufliche Stellung nach dem letzten Umzug; Branchenzugehörigkeit des Betriebs der ersten bezahlten Tätigkeit nach dem Umzug; befristetes Arbeitsverhältnis; Vorgesetztenfunktion; Anzahl Personen, für die Weisungsbefugnis bestand; Anzahl Beschäftigte des Gesamtunternehmens. 
Ehemalige Selbständige und Freiberufler: Branche; Anzahl der Mitarbeiter. 
Nicht-Erwerbstätige: Absicht zur (Wieder) Aufnahme einer Erwerbstätigkeit; Zeitpunkt der geplanten (Wieder) Aufnahme einer Erwerbstätigkeit; Wunsch nach Ausübung einer bestimmten beruflichen Tätigkeit; für die Tätigkeit erforderliche Ausbildung; amtliche Zulassung oder Erlaubnis zur Ausübung dieser beruflichen Tätigkeit vorhanden; Ausübung der Tätigkeit auch ohne amtliche Zulassung oder Erlaubnis möglich; Einschätzung der Chancen auf dem Arbeitsmarkt.
Rentner: Bezug von Rentenzahlungen; Gründe für den Rentenbezug; derzeitige Erwerbstätigkeit im Rahmen einer Nebentätigkeit; beabsichtigte Erwerbstätigkeit oder kein Interesse an einer Erwerbstätigkeit; Gründe für die (beabsichtigte) Erwerbstätigkeit bzw. Gründe gegen eine Erwerbstätigkeit während des Ruhestands.
Studierende: dasselbe Studium wie zum Zeitpunkt der letzten Befragung; Art der Studienfinanzierung. 
Veränderung durch den Umzug in das Aufenthaltsland (gleicher Arbeitgeber wie vorher, Tochterfirma des letzten Arbeitgebers oder ein ganz anderer Arbeitgeber); aktueller Auslandsaufenthalt / Aufenthalt in Deutschland ist Teil eines organisierten Mobilitätsprogramms (TEMPUS, ERASMUS (MUNDUS), LINGUA, anderes Mobilitätsprogramm).
Beginn der ersten beruflichen Tätigkeit (Monat, Jahr); aktuelle Tätigkeit noch in derselben Stelle und beim selben Arbeitgeber; Arbeitsstätte der ersten beruflichen Tätigkeit in Deutschland; berufliche Stellung der ersten beruflichen Tätigkeit; Tätigkeit und Branchenzugehörigkeit des damaligen Betriebs; Vorgesetztenfunktion; Anzahl der Personen, für die Weisungsbefugnis bestand; Berufswechsel; Jahr des Berufswechsels in den derzeit ausgeübten Beruf; im ersten Job Selbständige oder Freiberufler: damals ausgeübte berufliche Tätigkeit; damalige Branchenzugehörigkeit des Betriebs; Anzahl der Mitarbeiter; Berufswechsel; Jahr des Berufswechsels in den derzeit ausgeübten Beruf.
5. Einstellungen, Persönlichkeit und Wohlbefinden: Zufriedenheit mit verschiedenen Lebensbereichen; soziale Isolation (Gesellschaft anderer fehlt, außen vor sein, sozial isoliert sein); Selbsteinschätzung des Gesundheitszustands; Einschränkungen durch gesundheitliche Probleme im Alltag; Einschränkungen beim Treppensteigen; Gefühlslage in den letzten vier Wochen (niedergeschlagen oder trübsinnig, ruhig und ausgeglichen, viel Energie, weniger Arbeit geschafft/ Arbeit weniger sorgfältig wegen mentaler oder emotionaler Probleme, eingeschränkte Sozialkontakte wegen mentaler oder emotionaler Probleme); Institutionenvertrauen (deutscher Bundestag, Justizsystem in Deutschland, Polizei in Deutschland); Institutionenvertrauen im Migrationsland (Parlament, Justiz und Polizei); Sorgen im Hinblick auf verschiedene Bereiche (wirtschaftliche Entwicklung, eigene wirtschaftliche Lage, eigene Altersversorgung, Gesundheit, Klimawandel, Kriminalität in Deutschland, Zukunft der EU, Zuwanderung nach Deutschland, Fremdenhass in Deutschland, Sicherheit des Arbeitsplatzes); allgemeine Lebenszufriedenheit.
Demographie: Geschlecht; Migrationshintergrund; deutsche Staatsangehörigkeit; Sprachkenntnisse: Muttersprache; andere Sprache als Deutsch im Aufenthaltsland; Selbsteinschätzung der Kenntnisse der Sprache des Aufenthaltslandes; Kenntnisse der Landessprache in der Schule erworben; Bemühungen zur Verbesserung der Sprachkenntnisse; überwiegend gesprochene Sprache mit Familienmitgliedern, Freunden und am Arbeitsplatz; finanzielle Situation des Haushalts.
Soziodemografischer und sozioökonomischer Status des Partners des Befragten: Alter (Geburtsjahr); in Deutschland geboren; deutsche Staatsangehörigkeit; Schulabschluss; abgeschlossene Berufsausbildung; Art des Ausbildungs- oder Studienabschlusses; Erwerbsstatus.
Elterlicher/ sozialer Hintergrund: deutsche Staatsangehörigkeit; höchster allgemeinbildender Schulabschluss; Berufsausbildung oder Hochschulstudium; berufliche Stellung; Charakteristika der beruflichen Tätigkeit während der Jugend des Befragten; aufgewachsen mit beiden Eltern bzw. Situation während der ersten 15 Lebensjahre des Befragten. Zusätzlich verkodet wurde: Panel ID; Befragter ist mit der Person aus Welle 1 identisch; GERPS-Gruppe Welle 2; Jahr und Monat des Interviews; Bleibewahrscheinlichkeit (Welle 1 nach Welle 2); Original Sample; Gewichtungsfaktor.
Abgeleitete Variablen: Region (aktuelles Aufenthaltsland); Partner Status W 2; Trennung vom Partner zwischen Welle 1 und Welle 2; neue feste Partnerschaft zwischen Welle 1 und Welle 2; Veränderung der Haushaltszusammensetzung; Haushaltsgröße Welle 2; aktueller Familienstand; aktueller Partner im Haushalt; aktueller Haushaltsstatus (1-Stelle und 2-Stellen); Haushaltsstatus W 2; Anzahl der Kinder unter 17 Jahren im Haushalt W 2; Alter des jüngsten Kindes im Haushalt; Kinder im Haushalt unter 6, von 6 bis unter 12 und von 12 bis unter 17 Jahren; Bildung: Klassifizierung nach ISCED 11 und Casmin; höchster Schulabschluss; höchster beruflicher Bildungsabschluss und Hochschulabschluss des Befragten und des Partners W 2; aktueller Erwerbsstatus des Befragten und des Partners W 2; aktuell vertraglich vereinbarte Wochenarbeitszeit in Stunden und tatsächliche Wochenarbeitszeit W 2; aktuell vertragliches  und tatsächliches Arbeitszeitarrangement W 2; ISEI 08 und Standard International Occupational Prestige Scale (SIOPS88); Resident Status W 2, in Deutschland geboren; International Standard Classification of Occupations (ISCO08) (one digit); German Classification of Occupations 2010 (KLDB2010 one digit); Geburtsjahr (klassiert); Alter des Partners (klassiert); Haushaltseinkommen; monatliches Nettogehalt und Bruttogehalt; Flag Variablen.</freetext>
			<descriptionType>TableOfContents</descriptionType>
		</description>
		<description>
			<language>en</language>
			<freetext>Objective:The German Emigration and Remigration Panel Study (GERPS) is the data base developed within the project “Individuelle Konsequenzen internationaler Migration im Lebensverlauf” funded by the German Research Foundation (DFG) (project number 345626236). GERPS follows an origin-based sampling approach which allows to study individual consequences of international migrations form a life-course perspective. Apart the migration process and the sociodemographic attributes of international mobiles, the objective of GERPS is to conduct longitudinal data across the four following life domains: Employment and Income, Family and Partnership, Health and Well-being, and Social Networks and Participation.
Method:The study design of GERPS exploits information from German registers within a multistage stratified probability sample of emigrants and remigrants with German citizenship aged between 20 and 70 with a documented international migration between July 2017 and June 2018. Currently GERPS is comprising four waves covering a period of 24 months. The first wave started in November 2018 and ended in February 2019. The second wave started in May 2019, six months after the beginning of wave 1. The third wave started in November 2019 and ended in January 2020, six months after the beginning of wave 2. The fourth wave is scheduled for November 2020. Wave 1 includes information about 4.545 emigrants and 6.465 remigrants.
Analytical potential &amp; Questionnaire:The research design complements traditional immigrant surveys conducted in major destination countries by surveying emigrants and remigrants from the perspective of the country of origin. The origin-based sampling approach has at least three major advantages compared to traditional approaches where samples are drawn from immigrants in their destination countries: First, it enables comparative studies of emigrants in various destination countries and of remigrants returning from different destination countries. Second, as GERPS is organized as SOEP-related study, the research design enables comparisons of the internationally mobile population with non-migrants staying in the country of origin by drawing on the German Socioeconomic Panel (SOEP). Third, the research design allows comparative studies on emigrants and remigrants, providing the opportunity to analyse consequences of international migration from at least two perspectives – shortly after emigration and shortly after return.
Each wave of GERPS covers questions on German migrant’s current living situation in the different areas of life, gradually enabling researchers to draw a picture of survey participants’ life course with every further wave. Additionally, each wave has its own focus: The first wave covers migration motives and the situation shortly before migration. This enables the realization of a hypothetical fifth retrospective measurement point, allowing researchers to reflect on causes and consequences of international migration right from the beginning. The second wave concentrates on income, labour market integration, and social background. The third wave covers in particular social and family relationships. The fourth wave will be supplemented by an open module.
The present study comprises the data for the second wave.</freetext>
			<descriptionType>Abstract</descriptionType>
		</description>
		<description>
			<language>en</language>
			<freetext>1. Screening module for recording moves since wave 1: move since the last survey; move within the city/municipality, to another city/municipality, (back) to Germany, (back) to the previous country or to another country; time of move; distance of the new dwelling from the old place of residence (open, distance category); reasons for move (e.g., own occupational reasons or occupational reasons of partner, family reasons, financial reasons, etc.); ease of getting along after move; experiences of disadvantage and preference in the country of residence. e.g., own professional reasons or partner´s professional reasons, family reasons, financial reasons, etc.); ease of getting along after the move; experiences of disadvantage and preference in the country of residence on the basis of origin.
2. Current living and housing situation: marital status, partnership and type of household: Household size; household composition remained the same, changed, or. Respondent has left previous household; household size at time of last interview; update of household composition information; change in household composition (person added, person left household); total number of persons in new household (household size) if respondent left previous household; stable partnership; move to Germany and new living environment; time of move to Germany; reasons and motives for move (back) to Germany; stay abroad planned only for a limited time; ease of getting along after move; driving force for move decision within partnership; partner´s move to Germany before/after respondent or at the same time already lived in Germany; time of move to current country of residence (country W2); contact with people in country before move abroad (close relatives, other relatives, work colleagues or other friends and acquaintances); reasons and motives for move abroad; ease of getting along after move; same partner at time of move abroad (country W2); driving force for move decision within partnership; partner´s move to country of residence before/after interviewee or at same time or already lived there; living situation three months before last emigration: time of move abroad (month and year); lived in Germany before move abroad; main job before move away from Germany.
3. Contacts with friends and relatives: Connection to Germany and planned moves: not in Germany since leaving; number of days in Germany; serious thoughts of moving to another country; reasons for intention to move; planned duration of stay abroad (country W2/ Germany) (one more year at most, a few more years, forever); planned duration of stay abroad in years; contacts with friends and relatives: Number of close friends/girlfriends; number of close friends in Germany, in current/previous country of residence, or in another country; intensity of contact with different groups in Germany (spouse/partner, parents, parents-in-law, siblings, grandchildren, grandparents, other relatives, close friends).
4. Employment biography (focus module wave 2):
Change in employment status since arrival: reasons for leaving self-employment; number of previous employers; start of employment for current employer (month and year); start and end of employment with first employer (month and year);; start of employment with current employer (month and year); currently not employed: previous employment; number of previous employers or previous self-employment; start and end of employment for first/last employer (month and year); previous job commitment prior to moving; source of information for this job; manner of termination of previous job; new job already in prospect at time of leaving; source of information for this new job; manner of termination of this previous job. 
Current employment situation: industry affiliation of the current company resp. at the time of the last interview; change in employer due to move to the country of residence; secondment by the employer; current job corresponds to the profession learned; training required for the job; official authorization or permit to perform the job in the current country of residence (country W2); job can also be performed without official authorization or permit; fixed-term employment relationship; supervisor function; Number of persons for whom authority to issue directives exists; number of employees in the company as a whole; place of work in the country of residence/Germany; place of work in another country; company ties (personal significance, sense of belonging, part of the family in the company); frequency of help received from colleagues; frequency of offers of help to colleagues; frequency of unfair criticism, harassment or exposure by colleagues and superiors; assessment of opportunities on the labor market.
Self-employed and freelancers: sector of the current enterprise or at the time of the last interview; number of employees; place of work in the country of residence/Germany; place of work in another country; weekly working hours; average monthly net income (categorized); current activity corresponds to the learned profession; training required for the activity; official license or permit to pursue the professional activity in the current country of residence (country W2); pursuit of the activity also possible without official license or permit; assessment of opportunities on the labor market.
Non-employed persons: professional position after the last move; industry affiliation of the enterprise of the first paid job after the move; temporary employment relationship; supervisor function; number of persons for whom authority to issue directives existed; number of employees of the total enterprise.
Former self-employed and freelancers: industry; number of employees.
Non-employed persons: intention to (re)take up gainful employment; time of planned (re)taking up gainful employment; desire to pursue a specific occupational activity; training required for the activity; official license or permit to pursue this occupational activity available; pursuit of the activity also possible without official license or permit; assessment of chances on the labor market.
Retirees: receiving pension payments; reasons for receiving pension; current gainful employment as part of a second job; intended gainful employment or no interest in gainful employment; reasons for (intended) gainful employment or reasons against gainful employment during retirement.
Students: same studies as at the time of the last interview; type of student financing.
Change due to moving to country of residence (same employer as before, subsidiary of last employer, or a completely different employer); current stay abroad / stay in Germany is part of an organized mobility program (TEMPUS, ERASMUS (MUNDUS), LINGUA, other mobility program).
Start of first professional activity (month, year); current activity still in the same job and with the same employer; place of work of the first professional activity in Germany; professional position of the first professional activity; activity and industry affiliation of the company at that time; supervisor function; number of persons for whom authority to issue directives existed; change of profession; year of change of profession to the profession currently practiced; in the first job self-employed or freelancer: Occupation held at the time; industry affiliation of the establishment at the time; number of employees; change of occupation; year of change of occupation to the occupation currently held.
5. Attitudes, personality and well-being: Satisfaction with different areas of life; social isolation (lacking company of others, being left out, being socially isolated); self-assessment of health status; limitations due to health problems in everyday life; limitations in climbing stairs; emotional state in the last four weeks (depressed or gloomy, calm and balanced, lots of energy, less work done/work less carefully because of mental or emotional problems, limited social contacts because of mental or emotional problems); Institutional trust (German Bundestag, judicial system in Germany, police in Germany); institutional trust in country of migration (parliament, judiciary and police); concerns regarding various areas (economic development, own economic situation, own old age provision, health, climate change, crime in Germany, future of EU, immigration to Germany, xenophobia in Germany, job security); general life satisfaction.
Demography: sex; migration background; German citizenship; language skills: Mother tongue; language other than German in country of residence; self-assessed knowledge of language of country of residence; knowledge of national language acquired at school; efforts to improve language skills; language spoken predominantly with family members, friends, and at work; financial situation of household.
Sociodemographic and socioeconomic status of respondent´s partner: age (year of birth); born in Germany; German citizenship; high school diploma; completed vocational training; type of training or degree; employment status.
Parental/social background: German citizenship; highest general education degree; vocational training or higher education; occupational status; characteristics of occupation during respondent´s youth; grew up with both parents or situation during first 15 years of respondent´s life.
Additionally coded: Panel ID; respondent is same as person from wave 1; GERPS group wave 2; year and month of interview; lead probability (wave 1 to wave 2); original sample; weighting factor.
Derived variables: Region (current country of residence); partner status W 2; separation from partner between wave 1 and wave 2; new steady partnership between wave 1 and wave 2; change in household composition; household size wave 2; current marital status; current partner in household; current household status (1-job and 2-job); household status W 2; number of children under 17 in household W 2; age of youngest child in household; children in household under 6, from 6 to under 12, and from 12 to under 17; education: ISCED 11 and Casmin classification; highest level of schooling; highest level of vocational education and tertiary education of respondent and partner W 2; current employment status of respondent and partner W 2; current contracted hours of work per week and actual hours of work per week W 2; current contracted hours of work and actual hours of work arrangement W 2; ISEI 08 and Standard International Occupational Prestige Scale (SIOPS88); resident status W 2, born in Germany; International Standard Classification of Occupations (ISCO08) (one digit); German Classification of Occupations 2010 (KLDB2010 one digit); year of birth (classified); age of partner (classified); household income; monthly net salary and gross salary; flag variables.</freetext>
			<descriptionType>TableOfContents</descriptionType>
		</description>
	</descriptions>
	<geographicCoverages>
		<geographicCoverage>
			<geographicCoverageControlled>DE</geographicCoverageControlled>
		</geographicCoverage>
	</geographicCoverages>
	<universes>
		<universe>
			<language>de</language>
			<sampled>Deutsche Staatsbürger im Alter zwischen 20 und 70 Jahren, die zwischen Juli 2017 und Juni 2018 entweder aus Deutschland ins Ausland gezogen sind oder aus dem Ausland zurückgekehrt sind.
</sampled>
		</universe>
		<universe>
			<language>en</language>
			<sampled>Emigrants and remigrants with German citizenship aged between 20 and 70 with a documented international migration between July 2017 and June 2018. </sampled>
		</universe>
	</universes>
	<samplings>
		<sampling>
			<language>de</language>
			<method>Wahrscheinlichkeitsauswahl: Mehrstufige Zufallsauswahl; Auswahlverfahren Kommentar: Stichprobenrahmen/-design (Welle 2)

Teilnehmer, die (1) in Welle 1 befragt wurden und (2) in Welle 1 Einladungen zu künftigen Umfragen zugestimmt haben, abzüglich der Ablehnungen.</method>
		</sampling>
		<sampling>
			<language>en</language>
			<method>Probability: Multistage; Sampling Procedure Comment: Sampling frame/ design (Wave 2) 

Participants who (1) were interviewed in wave 1 and (2) consented to future survey invitations in wave 1, net of refusals. </method>
		</sampling>
	</samplings>
	<temporalCoverages>
		<temporalCoverage>
			<temporalCoverageFormal>
				<startDate>
					<date>2019-05-28</date>
				</startDate>
				<endDate>
					<date>2019-08-06</date>
				</endDate>
			</temporalCoverageFormal>
		</temporalCoverage>
	</temporalCoverages>
	<timeDimensions>
		<timeDimension>
			<timeDimensionType>Longitudinal.Panel</timeDimensionType>
		</timeDimension>
	</timeDimensions>
	<contributors>
		<contributor>
			<institution>
				<institutionName>SOKO Institut, Bielefeld</institutionName>
				<contributorType>DataCollector</contributorType>
			</institution>
		</contributor>
		<contributor>
			<person>
				<firstName>Jean Philippe</firstName>
				<middleName/>
				<lastName>Décieux</lastName>
				<contributorType>DataCurator</contributorType>
				<affiliation>
					<affiliationName>University of Duisburg-Essen</affiliationName>
				</affiliation>
			</person>
		</contributor>
		<contributor>
			<person>
				<firstName>Marcel</firstName>
				<middleName/>
				<lastName>Erlinghagen</lastName>
				<contributorType>ProjectLeader</contributorType>
				<affiliation>
					<affiliationName>University of Duisburg-Essen</affiliationName>
				</affiliation>
			</person>
		</contributor>
		<contributor>
			<person>
				<firstName>Andreas</firstName>
				<middleName/>
				<lastName>Ette</lastName>
				<contributorType>ProjectMember</contributorType>
				<affiliation>
					<affiliationName>Federal Institute of Population Research</affiliationName>
				</affiliation>
			</person>
		</contributor>
		<contributor>
			<person>
				<firstName>Andreas</firstName>
				<middleName/>
				<lastName>Genoni</lastName>
				<contributorType>ProjectMember</contributorType>
				<affiliation>
					<affiliationName>Federal Institute of Population Research</affiliationName>
				</affiliation>
			</person>
		</contributor>
		<contributor>
			<person>
				<firstName>Jean</firstName>
				<middleName/>
				<lastName>Guedes Auditor</lastName>
				<contributorType>ProjectMember</contributorType>
				<affiliation>
					<affiliationName>Federal Institute of Population Research</affiliationName>
				</affiliation>
			</person>
		</contributor>
		<contributor>
			<person>
				<firstName>Lisa</firstName>
				<middleName/>
				<lastName>Mansfeld</lastName>
				<contributorType>ProjectMember</contributorType>
				<affiliation>
					<affiliationName>University of Duisburg-Essen</affiliationName>
				</affiliation>
			</person>
		</contributor>
		<contributor>
			<person>
				<firstName>Norbert</firstName>
				<middleName/>
				<lastName>Schneider</lastName>
				<contributorType>ProjectLeader</contributorType>
				<affiliation>
					<affiliationName>Federal Institute of Population Research</affiliationName>
				</affiliation>
			</person>
		</contributor>
		<contributor>
			<person>
				<firstName>Nils</firstName>
				<middleName/>
				<lastName>Witte</lastName>
				<contributorType>ProjectMember</contributorType>
				<affiliation>
					<affiliationName>Federal Institute of Population Research</affiliationName>
				</affiliation>
			</person>
		</contributor>
	</contributors>
	<collectionModes>
		<collectionMode><collectionModeType>SelfAdministeredQuestionnaire.WebBased</collectionModeType></collectionMode>
		<collectionMode>
			<collectionModesFree>
				<collectionModeFree>
					<language>de</language>
					<freetext>Beginnend mit der zweiten Welle wurde GERPS als "Web-only"-Umfrage organisiert, die sich auf E-Mail-Einladungen und -Erinnerungen sowie eine Online-Umfrageoberfläche stützte. Nur eine kleine Teilstichprobe ohne aktuelle und gültige E-Mail-Adressen wurde ausschließlich per Postversand kontaktiert.</freetext>
				</collectionModeFree>
				<collectionModeFree>
					<language>en</language>
					<freetext>Starting with the second wave, GERPS was organised as a ‘web-only’ survey relying on email invitations and reminders and an online survey interface. Only a small subsample without up-to-date and valid email addresses was contacted exclusively by postal mailing.</freetext>
				</collectionModeFree>
			</collectionModesFree>
		</collectionMode>
	</collectionModes>
	<dataSets>
		<dataSet>
			<unitType>Individual</unitType>
			<numberUnits>6989</numberUnits>
			<numberVariables>393</numberVariables>
		</dataSet>
	</dataSets>
	<notes>
		<note>
			<language>de</language>
			<text/>
		</note>
		<note>
			<language>en</language>
			<text/>
		</note>
	</notes>
	<relations>
		<relation>
			<identifier>10.4232/1.13751</identifier>
			<identifierType>DOI</identifierType>
			<relationType>IsNewVersionOf</relationType>
		</relation>
	</relations>
	<publications>
		<publication>
			<unstructuredPublication>
				<freetext>Ette, Andreas; Décieux, Jean P.; Erlinghagen, Marcel; Guedes Auditor, Jean; Mansfeld, Lisa; Sander, Nikola; Schneider, Norbert F.; Witte, Nils 2019a: German Emigration and Remigration Panel Study (GERPS): Neue GERPS-Daten über deutsche Aus- und Rückwandernde. In: Bevölkerungsforschung Aktuell 6-2019: 3–7. </freetext>
			</unstructuredPublication>
		</publication>
		<publication>
			<unstructuredPublication>
				<freetext>Décieux, Jean Philippe; Witte, Nils; Erlinghagen, Marcel; Ette, Andreas; Genoni, Andreas; Guedes Auditor, Jean; Knirsch, Frederik; Kühne, Simon; Mansfeld, Lisa; Schneider, Norbert F. (2021): German Emigration and Remigration Panel Study (GERPS): Documentation of the Second Wave. BiB Daten- und Methodenberichte 2/2021.
Wiesbaden: Bundesinstitut für Bevölkerungsforschung. </freetext>
			</unstructuredPublication>
		</publication></publications>
</resource>
