<resource xmlns="http://da-ra.de/schema/kernel-4" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://www.da-ra.de/dara/schemadefinitions/dara.xsd">
	<!--
da|ra 4.0 Documentation for Study 'Foreigners in Germany 1994
'
-->
	<!--
da|ra 4.0 Dokumentation für Studie 'Ausländer in Deutschland 1994
'
-->
	<resourceType>Dataset</resourceType>
	<resourceIdentifier>
		<identifier>ZA2847</identifier>
		<currentVersion>1.0.0</currentVersion>
	</resourceIdentifier>
	<titles>
		<title>
			<language>de</language>
			<titleName>Ausländer in Deutschland 1994
</titleName>
		</title>
		<title>
			<language>en</language>
			<titleName>Foreigners in Germany 1994
</titleName>
		</title>
	</titles>
	<creators>
		<creator>
			<institution>
				<institutionName>MARPLAN, Offenbach</institutionName>
			</institution>
		</creator>
	</creators>
	<dataURLs>
		<dataURL>https://search.gesis.org/research_data/ZA2847?doi=10.4232/1.2847</dataURL>
	</dataURLs>
	<doiProposal>10.4232/1.2847</doiProposal>
	<publicationDate>
		<year>1996</year>
	</publicationDate>
	<availability>
		<availabilityType>Download</availabilityType>
		<availabilityFree>
			<language>de</language>
			<freetext>A - Daten und Dokumente sind für die akademische Forschung und Lehre freigegeben.</freetext>
		</availabilityFree>
		<availabilityFree>
			<language>en</language>
			<freetext>A - Data and documents are released for academic research and teaching.</freetext>
		</availabilityFree>
	</availability>
	<rights>
		<right>
			<language>de</language>
			<freetext>Alle im GESIS DBK veröffentlichten Metadaten sind frei verfügbar unter den Creative Commons CC0 1.0 Universal Public Domain Dedication. GESIS bittet jedoch darum, dass Sie alle Metadatenquellen anerkennen und sie nennen, etwa die Datengeber oder jeglichen Aggregator, inklusive GESIS selbst. Für weitere Informationen siehe https://dbk.gesis.org/dbksearch/guidelines.asp?db=d </freetext>
		</right>
		<right>
			<language>en</language>
			<freetext>All metadata from GESIS DBK are available free of restriction under the Creative Commons CC0 1.0 Universal Public Domain Dedication. However, GESIS requests that you actively acknowledge and give attribution to all metadata sources, such as the data providers and any data aggregators, including GESIS. For further information see https://dbk.gesis.org/dbksearch/guidelines.asp </freetext>
		</right>
	</rights>
	<resourceLanguage>deu</resourceLanguage>
	<alternativeIDs>
		<alternativeID>
			<identifier>ZA2847</identifier>
			<type>ZA-No.</type>
		</alternativeID>
	</alternativeIDs>
	<classifications>
		<classification>
			<classificationInternal>
				<classificationSchemaType>ZA</classificationSchemaType>
				<identifiers>
					<identifier>KAT50</identifier>
					<!-- Gesellschaft, Kultur -->
				</identifiers>
			</classificationInternal>
		</classification>
		<classification>
			<classificationExternal>
				<language>de</language>
				<classificationSchema>CESSDA Topic Classification</classificationSchema>
				<terms>
					<term>Migration</term>
					<term>Soziale Lage und soziale Indikatoren</term>
				</terms>
			</classificationExternal>
		</classification>
		<classification>
			<classificationExternal>
				<language>en</language>
				<classificationSchema>CESSDA Topic Classification</classificationSchema>
				<terms>
					<term>Migration</term>
					<term>Social conditions and indicators</term>
				</terms>
			</classificationExternal>
		</classification>
	</classifications>
	<descriptions>
		<description>
			<language>de</language>
			<freetext>Die soziale und wirtschaftliche Situation ausländischerArbeitnehmer in der Bundesrepublik.
Themen: Nationalität des Befragten; ethnische Zugehörigkeitbei Befragten aus dem ehemaligen Jugoslawien; Geburtsort inDeutschland oder im Ausland; bisherige Aufenthaltsdauer inDeutschland; geschätzter Zeitraum, der noch in Deutschlandverbracht wird; Heimataufenthalte seit dem Umzug nachDeutschland; Heimataufenthalt im Vorjahr; geplanterHeimataufenthalt 1994; Verkehrsmittelnutzung bei Fahrten insHeimatland; Zusammensein mit Familienangehörigen inDeutschland; Anzahl und Alter der Kinder in Deutschland; Anzahlder berufstätigen Haushaltsmitglieder; Anzahl der über15jährigen im Haushalt; Familienmitglieder im Heimatland; Altervon Kindern im Heimatland; größte Sorgen und Probleme inDeutschland; Interesse an deutscher Staatsangehörigkeit;Kontakte zu Deutschen in verschiedenen Bereichen;Chancengleichheit von Ausländern und Deutschen bei derArbeitsplatzsuche; perzipierte Einstellung der Deutschen zuGastarbeitern am Arbeitsplatz; Zufriedenheit mit derzeitigemArbeitsplatz; Einschätzung des Verhältnisses von Deutschen undAusländern in Wohngegend; Präferenz für ein nachbarschaftlichesZusammenleben von Deutschen und Ausländern oder Segregation;sympathischste Partei in Deutschland; durchschnittlichemonatliche Ausgaben für Lebensmittel und Dinge des täglichenBedarfs; präferierte Kaufstätten für Lebensmittel und Dinge destäglichen Bedarfs sowie Gebrauchsgüter und Spielwaren;Wohnstatus; Miethöhe; Mieterhöhung für Grundmiete oderNebenkosten im letzten Jahr; Wohndauer in jetziger Wohnung;Anzahl der Wohnräume; Umzugsabsicht in den nächsten zweiJahren; Zufriedenheit mit Wohnung/Unterkunft; Anzahl derabsolvierten Schuljahre; Schulabschluß in Deutschland oderHeimat; Art des Schulabschlusses; Selbsteinschätzung derDeutschkenntnisse (Lesen); abgeschlossene Berufsausbildungsowie Dauer der Berufsausbildung; PKW-Besitz; PKW-Marke; Neu-oder Gebrauchtwagen; jährliche Kilometerleistung;Haushaltsnettoeinkommen.
Demographie: Alter; Familienstand; Beruf; Berufstätigkeit; Einkommen.
Interviewerrating: Anwesenheit Dritter beim Interview sowieBeeinflussung durch Dritte; Bewertung der Verständigung;Kooperationsbereitschaft des Befragten; Kenntnisse derdeutschen und der eigenen Sprache; Lage der Wohnung inStadtnähe; Wohnhaustyp; Hochhausviertel.
Zusätzlich verkodet wurde: Bundesland; Ortskennziffer;Ortsgröße.</freetext>
			<descriptionType>Abstract</descriptionType>
		</description>
		<description>
			<language>en</language>
			<freetext>The social and economic situation of foreign workers in the FederalRepublic. Topics: nationality of respondent; ethnic affiliation ofrespondents from former Yugoslavia; place of birth in Germany orabroad; duration of stay in Germany up to now; estimated time periodthat will still be spent in Germany; visits to one´s native countrysince moving to Germany; visit to one´s native country in the previousyear; planned visit to one´s native country 1994; use of various meansof transport for trips to the native country; being together withfamily members in Germany; number and ages of children in Germany;number of members of household working; number of persons over 15 yearsin household; family members in native country; age of children innative country; greatest concerns and problems in Germany; interest inGerman citizenship; contacts with Germans in various areas; equalopportunities of foreigners and Germans in the search for work;perceived attitude of Germans to guest workers at work; satisfactionwith current job; assessment of the relationship of Germans andforeigners in residential area; preference for Germans and foreignersliving together as neighbors or segregation; most sympathetic party inGermany; average monthly expenditures for food and everydaynecessities; preferred shopping places for food and everydaynecessities as well as consumer goods and toys; residential status;amount of rent; rent increase for base rent or additional costs in thelast year; length of residence in current residence; number ofliving-rooms; intent to move in the next two years; satisfaction withapartment/housing; number of years of school completed; school degreein Germany or native country; type of school degree; self-assessment ofknowledge of German (reading); completed vocational training as well aslength of vocational training; possession of a car; brand of car; newor used car; number of kilometers driven annually; net householdincome. Interviewer rating: presence of third persons during interviewas well as influence through third parties; evaluation ofcommunication; willingness of respondent to cooperate; knowledge ofGerman and one´s own language; location of residence in city vicinity;type of residential building; high-rise part of town. Also encoded was:state; city code; city size. </freetext>
			<descriptionType>Abstract</descriptionType>
		</description>
	</descriptions>
	<geographicCoverages>
		<geographicCoverage>
			<geographicCoverageControlled>DE</geographicCoverageControlled>
			<geographicCoveragesFree>
				<geographicCoverageFree>
					<language>en</language>
					<freetext>old states and West Berlin</freetext>
				</geographicCoverageFree>
				<geographicCoverageFree>
					<language>de</language>
					<freetext>alte Bundesländer und Berlin-West </freetext>
				</geographicCoverageFree>
			</geographicCoveragesFree>
		</geographicCoverage>
	</geographicCoverages>
	<universes>
		<universe>
			<language>de</language>
			<sampled>Ausländische Wohnbevölkerung ab 14 Jahren (Türken, Italiener,
Jugoslawen, Griechen und Spanier) </sampled>
		</universe>
		<universe>
			<language>en</language>
			<sampled>Foreign residential population 14 years old and older (Spaniards, Italians, Yugoslavs, Greeks and Turks over-sample according to nationalities)</sampled>
		</universe>
	</universes>
	<samplings>
		<sampling>
			<language>de</language>
			<method>Auswahlverfahren Kommentar: Quotenauswahl nach Geschlecht, Alter, Familienstand und Haushaltsgröße,
je etwa 400 Personen pro Nationalität </method>
		</sampling>
		<sampling>
			<language>en</language>
			<method>Sampling Procedure Comment: Quota sample according to sex, age, marital status and size of household, about 400 persons per nationality
</method>
		</sampling>
	</samplings>
	<temporalCoverages>
		<temporalCoverage>
			<temporalCoverageFormal>
				<startDate>
					<monthyear>1994-04</monthyear>
				</startDate>
				<endDate>
					<monthyear>1994-05</monthyear>
				</endDate>
			</temporalCoverageFormal>
		</temporalCoverage>
	</temporalCoverages>
	<contributors>
		<contributor>
			<institution>
				<institutionName>MARPLAN, Offenbach
</institutionName>
				<contributorType>DataCollector</contributorType>
			</institution>
		</contributor>
	</contributors>
	<collectionModes>
		<collectionMode>
			<collectionModesFree>
				<collectionModeFree>
					<language>de</language>
					<freetext>Mündliche Befragung mit standardisiertem Fragebogen
</freetext>
				</collectionModeFree>
				<collectionModeFree>
					<language>en</language>
					<freetext>Oral survey with standardized questionnaire
</freetext>
				</collectionModeFree>
			</collectionModesFree>
		</collectionMode>
	</collectionModes>
	<dataSets>
		<dataSet>
			<numberVariables>129</numberVariables>
		</dataSet>
	</dataSets>
	<notes>
		<note>
			<language>de</language>
			<text>Die Studie ist Teil einer Mehrthemen-Erhebung und Teil einer
Befragungsserie, die 1970 begann.
</text>
		</note>
		<note>
			<language>en</language>
			<text>The study is part of an omnibus survey and part of a
survey series that began in 1970.
</text>
		</note>
	</notes>
</resource>
