<resource xmlns="http://da-ra.de/schema/kernel-4" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://www.da-ra.de/dara/schemadefinitions/dara.xsd">
	<!--
da|ra 4.0 Documentation for Study 'Foreign Workers in the Federal Republic (1982) 
'
-->
	<!--
da|ra 4.0 Dokumentation für Studie 'Ausländische Arbeitnehmer in der Bundesrepublik (1982)
'
-->
	<resourceType>Dataset</resourceType>
	<resourceIdentifier>
		<identifier>ZA1329</identifier>
		<currentVersion>1.0.0</currentVersion>
	</resourceIdentifier>
	<titles>
		<title>
			<language>de</language>
			<titleName>Ausländische Arbeitnehmer in der Bundesrepublik (1982)
</titleName>
		</title>
		<title>
			<language>en</language>
			<titleName>Foreign Workers in the Federal Republic (1982) 
</titleName>
		</title>
	</titles>
	<creators>
		<creator>
			<institution>
				<institutionName>MARPLAN, Offenbach</institutionName>
			</institution>
		</creator>
	</creators>
	<dataURLs>
		<dataURL>https://search.gesis.org/research_data/ZA1329?doi=10.4232/1.1329</dataURL>
	</dataURLs>
	<doiProposal>10.4232/1.1329</doiProposal>
	<publicationDate>
		<year>1984</year>
	</publicationDate>
	<availability>
		<availabilityType>Download</availabilityType>
		<availabilityFree>
			<language>de</language>
			<freetext>A - Daten und Dokumente sind für die akademische Forschung und Lehre freigegeben.</freetext>
		</availabilityFree>
		<availabilityFree>
			<language>en</language>
			<freetext>A - Data and documents are released for academic research and teaching.</freetext>
		</availabilityFree>
	</availability>
	<rights>
		<right>
			<language>de</language>
			<freetext>Alle im GESIS DBK veröffentlichten Metadaten sind frei verfügbar unter den Creative Commons CC0 1.0 Universal Public Domain Dedication. GESIS bittet jedoch darum, dass Sie alle Metadatenquellen anerkennen und sie nennen, etwa die Datengeber oder jeglichen Aggregator, inklusive GESIS selbst. Für weitere Informationen siehe https://dbk.gesis.org/dbksearch/guidelines.asp?db=d </freetext>
		</right>
		<right>
			<language>en</language>
			<freetext>All metadata from GESIS DBK are available free of restriction under the Creative Commons CC0 1.0 Universal Public Domain Dedication. However, GESIS requests that you actively acknowledge and give attribution to all metadata sources, such as the data providers and any data aggregators, including GESIS. For further information see https://dbk.gesis.org/dbksearch/guidelines.asp </freetext>
		</right>
	</rights>
	<resourceLanguage>deu</resourceLanguage>
	<alternativeIDs>
		<alternativeID>
			<identifier>ZA1329</identifier>
			<type>ZA-No.</type>
		</alternativeID>
	</alternativeIDs>
	<classifications>
		<classification>
			<classificationInternal>
				<classificationSchemaType>ZA</classificationSchemaType>
				<identifiers>
					<identifier>KAT50</identifier>
					<!-- Gesellschaft, Kultur -->
				</identifiers>
			</classificationInternal>
		</classification>
		<classification>
			<classificationExternal>
				<language>de</language>
				<classificationSchema>CESSDA Topic Classification</classificationSchema>
				<terms>
					<term>Migration</term>
					<term>Soziale Lage und soziale Indikatoren</term>
					<term>Medien</term>
					<term>Einkommen, Vermögen und Geldanlagen/Sparen</term>
					<term>Konsum und Konsumverhalten</term>
				</terms>
			</classificationExternal>
		</classification>
		<classification>
			<classificationExternal>
				<language>en</language>
				<classificationSchema>CESSDA Topic Classification</classificationSchema>
				<terms>
					<term>Migration</term>
					<term>Social conditions and indicators</term>
					<term>Media</term>
					<term>Income, property and investment/saving</term>
					<term>Consumption and consumer behaviour</term>
				</terms>
			</classificationExternal>
		</classification>
	</classifications>
	<descriptions>
		<description>
			<language>de</language>
			<freetext>Die soziale und wirtschaftliche Situation der ausländischenArbeitnehmer in der Bundesrepublik. Konsumverhalten undGeldfragen.
Themen: 1.) Zur wirtschaftlichen und sozialen Situation:Derzeitige und beabsichtigte weitere Aufenthaltsdauer in derBRD; Häufigkeit von Heimatbesuchen in den letzten Jahren;präferierter Reisemonat und benutztes Verkehrsmittel;Familienangehörige in der Bundesrepublik; Zeitpunkt des Zuzugsder Familienmitglieder; größte Sorgen und Schwierigkeiten inder Bundesrepublik; vermutete Einstellung der Deutschen zuGastarbeitern; Beurteilung des Einsatzes von Gewerkschaften,Behörden, Organisationen und Verbänden und anderen Gruppen fürdie Probleme ausländischer Arbeitnehmer; wichtigste Aufgabender Gewerkschaften; Arbeitsplatzzufriedenheit; Interesse an derdeutschen Staatsbürgerschaft; Parteipräferenz.
2.) Geldfragen: Kenntnis und Nutzung vonGeldanlagemöglichkeiten; Höhe des Gesamtbetrages auf deutschenSparkonten; Name des Kreditinstitutes; Bekanntheitsgrad vonBausparkassen; Anzahl der abgeschlossenen Bausparverträge inder Bundesrepublik; Abschlußjahr des Vertrages; Vermittler;Sparzweck; Kontakt zu Bankmitarbeitern nach Abschluß desBausparvertrages; Höhe der Geldüberweisungen und Geldmitnahmein die Heimat durch den Befragten bzw. Haushaltsmitglieder.
3.) Rauchverhalten: Häufigkeit des Rauchens ausgewählterTabakprodukte; präferierte Marke; Zigarettenkonsum pro Tag;Wechsel der Zigarettenmarke; Einkaufsort und Automatenkäufe;Rauchverhalten am Vortag in Form präferierter und sonstigerMarken; Umfang und Marken der in die Heimat mitgenommenenZigaretten.
4.) Konsumverhalten und sonstiges: Präferierte Kaffeeart;täglicher Kaffeekonsum und Zubereitungsart sowie Marke; Antragauf Lohnsteuerjahresausgleich gestellt und in Anspruchgenommene Hilfe; Besitz und Bekanntheitsgrad vonElektrogeräten; Beurteilung der eigenen derzeitigenwirtschaftlichen Lage und der zukünftigen Entwicklung;Einschätzung der beruflichen Chancen im Vergleich zu deutschenArbeitnehmern; Religionszugehörigekit und Religiosität(Kirchgangshäufigkeit); Änderung der Zukunftspläne der Familiewegen der Ausländererlasse; Arbeitslosigkeit; Kurzarbeit;Industriezweig; Wohnsituation und Wohnzufriedenheit;Schulbesuchsdauer; tatsächliche Miethöhe und maximalvertretbare Kosten; PKW-Besitz und Marke; Neukauf oderGebrauchtwagenkauf; Autoradiobesitz und Marke; gelesenedeutsche Zeitschriften und Zeitungen.
Demographie: Alter; Geschlecht; Berufsausbildung; Beruf;Berufstätigkeit; Branche des Betriebes; Einkommen; Wohnstatus;Bundesland.
Interviewerrating: Ortsgröße; Störungen des Interviewablaufs;Einschätzung der Verständigungsmöglichkeiten; Kooperationsbereitschaftdes Befragten; Einschätzung der Kenntnisse der Landessprache sowie derdeutschen Sprache.</freetext>
			<descriptionType>Abstract</descriptionType>
		</description>
		<description>
			<language>en</language>
			<freetext>The social and economic situation of foreign workers in the FederalRepublic. Consumer habits and money questions. 
Topics: 1. Economic and social situation: current and intended furtherlength of stay in the FRG; frequency of home visits in the last fewyears; preferred travel month and means of transport used; familymembers in the Federal Republic; time of moving to Germany by familymembers; greatest concerns and difficulties in the Federal Republic;assumed attitude of Germans to guest workers; judgement on the effortof trade unions, authorities, organizations and associations and othergroups for the problems of foreign workers; most important tasks oftrade unions; job satisfaction; interest in German citizenship; partypreference. 
2. Money questions: knowledge and use of investment possibilities;amount of total sum in German savings accounts; name of creditinstitute; degree of familiarity of loan and building associations;number of completed building loan contracts in the Federal Republic;year of completion of contract; agent; savings purpose; contact withbank employees after completing the building loan contract; amount ofmoney transfers and money taken home by the respondent or members ofhousehold. 
3. Smoking habits: frequency of smoking selected tobacco products;preferred brand; use of cigarettes per day; change of brand ofcigarettes; shopping place and purchase from machine; smoking behavioryesterday in form of personal, preferred brand and other brands; extentand brands of cigarettes taken home. 
4. Consumer habits and miscellaneous: preferred type of coffee; dailycoffee consumption and manner of preparation as well as brand;submitting income tax return and assistance used; possession and degreeof familiarity of electric equipment; judgement on one´s own currenteconomic situation and future development; assessment of occupationalchances in comparison to German workers; religious affiliation andreligiousness (frequence of church attendance); change of future plansof the family due to the foreigner decrees; unemployment; short timework; industry branch; housing situation and satisfaction with housing;length of school attendance; actual amount of rent and maximumjustifiable costs; car possession and brand; purchased new or used; carradio possession and brand; German magazines and newspapers read. 
Demography: age; sex; occupational training; occupation employment;area of business of company; income; residential status; state. 
Interviewer rating: city size; disturbances of the course of theinterview; assessment of the ability to communicate; willingness ofrespondent to cooperate; assessment of knowledge of national languageas well as of the German language. </freetext>
			<descriptionType>Abstract</descriptionType>
		</description>
	</descriptions>
	<geographicCoverages>
		<geographicCoverage>
			<geographicCoverageControlled>DE</geographicCoverageControlled>
			<geographicCoveragesFree>
				<geographicCoverageFree>
					<language>en</language>
					<freetext>FRG incl. West Berlin</freetext>
				</geographicCoverageFree>
				<geographicCoverageFree>
					<language>de</language>
					<freetext>BRD einschl. West-Berlin </freetext>
				</geographicCoverageFree>
			</geographicCoveragesFree>
		</geographicCoverage>
	</geographicCoverages>
	<universes>
		<universe>
			<language>de</language>
			<sampled>Türken, Italiener, Jugoslawen, Griechen und Spanier</sampled>
		</universe>
		<universe>
			<language>en</language>
			<sampled>Turks, Italians, Yugoslavs, Greeks and Spaniards</sampled>
		</universe>
	</universes>
	<samplings>
		<sampling>
			<language>de</language>
			<method>Auswahlverfahren Kommentar: Quotenauswahl nach Geschlecht, Alter und Zugangsjahr
</method>
		</sampling>
		<sampling>
			<language>en</language>
			<method>Sampling Procedure Comment: Quota sample according to sex, age and arrival year  </method>
		</sampling>
	</samplings>
	<temporalCoverages>
		<temporalCoverage>
			<temporalCoverageFormal>
				<startDate>
					<monthyear>1982-03</monthyear>
				</startDate>
			</temporalCoverageFormal>
		</temporalCoverage>
	</temporalCoverages>
	<contributors>
		<contributor>
			<institution>
				<institutionName>MARPLAN, Offenbach 
</institutionName>
				<contributorType>DataCollector</contributorType>
			</institution>
		</contributor>
	</contributors>
	<collectionModes>
		<collectionMode>
			<collectionModesFree>
				<collectionModeFree>
					<language>de</language>
					<freetext>Mündliche Befragung mit standardisiertem Fragebogen
</freetext>
				</collectionModeFree>
				<collectionModeFree>
					<language>en</language>
					<freetext>Oral survey with standardized questionnaire. 
</freetext>
				</collectionModeFree>
			</collectionModesFree>
		</collectionMode>
	</collectionModes>
	<dataSets>
		<dataSet>
			<numberVariables>563</numberVariables>
		</dataSet>
	</dataSets>
	<notes>
		<note>
			<language>de</language>
			<text>Die Interviews wurden von speziell für diese Aufgabe
geschulten Interviewern, die über Grundkenntnisse der
jeweiligen Landessprache verfügten, durchgeführt. Um eine
Standardisierung der Befragung zu ermöglichen, wurden die
kompletten Erhebungsunterlagen zweisprachig bearbeitet, d.h.
Fragen und Antwortvorgaben lagen dem Befragten in seiner
jeweiligen Landessprache schriftlich vor; der Interviewer
notierte die Angaben in einem deckungsgleichen
Fragebogenexemplar.
Die Studie ist Teil einer Mehrthemen-Erhebung und Teil einer
Trend-Erhebung.
Weitere "Ausländerstudien" aus dieser Reihe sind unter den
folgenden ZA-Studien-Nrn. archiviert:
ZA-Studien-Nr. 0606 (1970)
ZA-Studien-Nr. 0607 (1971)
ZA-Studien-Nr. 0608 (1972)
ZA-Studien-Nr. 0676 (1973)
ZA-Studien-Nr. 0677 (1974)
ZA-Studien-Nr. 0928 (1975)
ZA-Studien-Nr. 0929 (1976)
ZA-Studien-Nr. 1075 (1977)
ZA-Studien-Nr. 1076 (1978)
ZA-Studien-Nr. 1077 (1979)
ZA-Studien-Nr. 1328 (1980)
ZA-Studien-Nr. 1358 (Datenpool 1970-1982)
ZA-Studien-Nr. 1629 (1984)
ZA-Studien-Nr. 1630 (1985)
ZA-Studien-Nr. 1631 (1986)
ZA-Studien-Nr. 1678 (1988)
</text>
		</note>
		<note>
			<language>en</language>
			<text>The interviews were conducted by interviewers specially schooled for 
this task and having basic knowledge of the respective national 
language. To make standardization of the survey possible the complete 
survey documents were processed in two languages, i.e. questions and 
possible responses were available to the respondent in his respective 
national language; the interviewer noted responses in an identical 
copy of the questionnaire. The study is part of an omnibus survey and 
part of a trend survey. The remaining "foreigner studies" from this 
series are archived under the following ZA Study Nos.: 
ZA Study No. 0606 (1970) 
ZA Study No. 0607 (1971) 
ZA Study No. 0608 (1972) 
ZA Study No. 0676 (1973) 
ZA Study No. 0677 (1974) 
ZA Study No. 0928 (1975) 
ZA Study No. 0929 (1976) 
ZA Study No. 1075 (1977) 
ZA Study No. 1076 (1978) 
ZA Study No. 1077 (1979) 
ZA Study No. 1329 (1982) 
ZA Study No. 1358 (data pool 1970-1982) 
ZA Study No. 1629 (1984) 
ZA Study No. 1630 (1985) 
ZA Study No. 1631 (1986) 
ZA Study No. 1678 (1988) 
</text>
		</note>
	</notes>
</resource>
